Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Library of Congress
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Manuscripts, 1859-1892 and undated (Box 1)
  - A starry midnight, about 1881; loc.00083; xxx.00291; poetry 1 leaf 21 cm x 13 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder A Clear Midnight)
    A draft of a poem entitled A starry midnight, published as A Clear Midnight in 1881. At the top is a note in blue pencil that reads "? for end of poems"
  - Thou Orb Aloft, about 1881; loc.00084; xxx.00270; poetry 2 leaves 11 cm x 19 cm to 23 cm x 19 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Thou Orb Aloft Full-Dazzling)
    A two-page draft of the poem published first in 1881 as A Summer Invocation, then published later that year with the title Thou Orb Aloft Full-Dazzling.
  - [you ye ebbing], about 1885; loc.00086; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of Last Ebb, and Daylight Waning, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [firm strong], about 1885; loc.05102; xxx.00333; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of You Tides with Ceaseless Swell, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Last of the ebb], about 1885; loc.00087; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [Half-caught promises], about 1885; loc.00355; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [How they sweep down and out!], about 1885; loc.00356; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [You neighboring surf—], about 1885; loc.00357; xxx.00337; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of By that Long Scan of Waves, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Back to these fathomless deeps returning], about 1885; loc.00358; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Till from the ostent], about 1885; loc.04145; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [rivers', bays' and ocean shores'], about 1885; loc.04146; xxx.00335; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of And Yet Not You Alone, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Nor you and yours alone], about 1885; loc.04147; xxx.00335; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [How strange the scenes], about 1885; loc.04148; xxx.00337; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of By That Long Scan of Waves, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [What ventures, aspirations, failures—], about 1885; loc.04149; xxx.00335; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [Nor rivers' bays' and ocean], about 1885; loc.04150; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in 1885.
  - [Then deeper], about 1885; loc.04167; xxx.00338; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of Then Last of All, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [What spells do distant stars], about 1885; loc.04168; xxx.00333; handwritten poetry correspondence 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Drafts lines of You Tides with Ceaseless Swell, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink. On the verso is correspondence on the letterhead of Bim M. Jordan, Dry Paints, Pine Wood Products.
  - [With many a voice], about 1885; loc.04155; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [Nor you and trail of yours], about 1885; loc.04156; xxx.00335; xxx.00338; xxx.00336; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines of poems in the Fancies at Navesink cluster, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ). Lines on the recto resemble those in And Yet Not You Alone and Then Last of All. The verso contains lines for Proudly the Flood Comes In.
  - [What burnt-out lives], about 1885; loc.04157; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in THe Nineteenth Century ( August 1885.
  - [swell and ebb!], about 1885; loc.04159; xxx.00338; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [What fiat sends ye out], about 1885; loc.04153; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteent Century ( August 1885 ).
  - [But Liquid utterance], about 1885; loc.04152; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Ephemeral scenes], about 1885; loc.04151; xxx.00337; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for By That Long Scan of Waves, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [What unhelm'd ships and boats], about 1885; loc.04166; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ).
  - [You whirling stream's wild currents], about 1885; loc.04160; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885.
  - [Smells of the sedge and the shore], about 1885; loc.04161; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for the poem Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Souls of the dying float out with you], about 1885; loc.04164; xxx.00330; xxx.00344; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885. The verso of contains draft and trial lines for Of That Blithe Throat of Thine, first published in Harper's Monthly Magazine ( January 1885 ).
  - [Swelling and ebbing the tides], about 1885; loc.04165; xxx.00333; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft titles for You Tides with Ceaseless Swell, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [O ebbing tide!], about 1885; loc.04175; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [Voices of Ebb Tide], about 1885; loc.04169; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Trial title for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ).
  - [Proudly the flood comes in], about 1885; loc.04170; xxx.00336; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Proudly the Flood Come In, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [The human heart in its breast], about 1885; loc.04171; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [The land itself], about 1885; loc.04163; xxx.00336; handwritten poetry correspondence 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Proudly the Flood Come In, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink. On the verso is a letter from an autograph-seeker.
  - [Ebb—Tide], about 1885; loc.04176; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [Echoes of Ebb Tide], about 1885; loc.04172; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( 1885 ).
  - [Ebb Tide Ripples], about 1885; loc.04173; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Trial titles for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ).
  - [Ebb—Tide ripples whisperings], about 1885; loc.04174; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [Mainsails and topsails], about 1885; loc.04177; xxx.00336; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Proudly the Flood Comes In, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Ebb tide's and death's], about 1885; loc.04178; xxx.00330; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century August 1885.
  - [What potent spells], about 1885; loc.05103; xxx.00333; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    A draft line for You Tides with Ceaseless Swell, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [worldly and gaily comes], about 1885; loc.05104; xxx.00336; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [With many a hurried abrupt confession], about 1885; loc.05113; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [To you your cosmic], about 1885; loc.05114; xxx.00338; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
    Draft lines for Then Last of All, first published along with seven other poems in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), under the general title Fancies at Navesink.
  - [Gaily the outward bound], about 1885; loc.05115; xxx.00338; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - [How ye sweep down and out!], about 1885; loc.05117; xxx.00334; handwritten poetry 1 leaf 3 cm x 15 cm to 25 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder Fancies at Navesink)
  - Sparse, wintry little leaves, about 1887; loc.00359; xxx.00368; poetry 1 leaf 23.5 cm x 15 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me)
    A draft of a poem entitled Sparse, wintry, little leaves. The poem was later revised and published as You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me in 1887.
  - [To-Day at the peak], about 1888; loc.00360; xxx.00646; poetry correspondence 1 leaf 28 cm x 21 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Glad the Jaunts for the Known)
    Draft of one or possibly two poems beginning "To-Day at the peak" and "Glad the jaunts for the known." Lines from this manuscript were published posthumously as [Glad the Jaunts for the Known]. On the verso is a letter, dated January, 1888, from James G. Bennett, editor of the New York Herald.
  - A Song for Sweet Water, July, 1890; loc.00361; xxx.00647; poetry 1 leaf 28 cm x 21.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder A Song for Sweet Water)
    Notes and trial lines for a poem to commemorate "the new water works" entitled A Song for Sweet Water, subtitled "Pure, general sweet water." A note at the bottom of the document gives the date as July, 1890.
  - For us two, reader dear, about 1890; loc.00362; xxx.00566; poetry correspondence 1 leaf 22.5 cm x 17.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder For us Two, Reader Dear)
    A draft of the poem For Us Two, Reader Dear, first published in 1891. Also on the leaf is a letter to Whitman dated June 4, 1890 from Mrs. Noble T. Biddle.
  - Grand is the seen, about 1891; loc.00363; xxx.00408; poetry correspondence 1 leaf 12.5 cm x 20.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Grand is the Seen)
    A draft of the poem Grand is the Seen, first published in 1891. On the verso is the end of a letter from R. Rooke Morgau.
  - L. of G.'s Purport, about 1891; loc.00364; xxx.00406; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder L.of G.'s Purport)
    A draft of the first two lines of L. of G.'s Purport, first published in 1891.
  - This Journey, about 1891; loc.00365; xxx.00406; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder L. of G.'s Purport)
    A draft entitled This Journey (the manuscript suggests Whitman was also considering the title My Task), later incorporated as lines 6, 7, 8, and 9 in L. of G.'s Purport, first published in 1891. Also on the leaf is an undated, cancelled letter.
  - This journey, about 1871–1874 and about 1891; loc.00366; xxx.00406; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder L. of G.'s Purport)
    Two drafts of a poem entitled This journey. The lines were later incorporated as lines 6, 7, 8, and 9 in L. of G.'s Purport, first published in 1891. On the verso are notes about "Payments to Mrs. White" between 1871 and 1874.
  - [Now for the P], about 1892; loc.00515; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 x 15.5 to 21 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
    Drafts and trial lines of the poem Supplement Hours, first published posthumously in 1897.
  - [Sane culminating hours], about 1892; loc.00516; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [Supplement hours of a half Paralytic], about 1892; loc.00517; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - Supplement Hours, about 1892; loc.00518; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - Supplement Hours, about 1892; loc.00519; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - Supplement Hours, about 1892; loc.00520; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [Sane, culminated random hours], about 1892; loc.00521; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [As wild bees hum], about 1892; loc.00522; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [Now Supplement Hours], about 1892; loc.00523; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
    Drafts and trial lines of the poem Supplement Hours, first published posthumously in 1897. On the verso is a prose manuscript recalling Whitman's Washington years. The prose manuscript has no known relationship to his published work.
  - [now away from books—], about 1892; loc.00524; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [the wild Bee flitting hums], about 1892; loc.00525; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [A September Supplement], about 1892; loc.00526; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - Supplement Hours, about 1892; loc.00527; xxx.00762; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 cm x 15.5 cm to 21 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder Supplement Hours)
  - [What cannot meet all], 1850-1890; loc.05179; xxx.00939; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    The recto of this manuscript is a prose jotting with no known relationship to Whitman's published work. On the verso is a draft poem which is partially illegible. The language used here reminds of many poems by Whitman, but, especially because the manuscript is partially illegible. The language used here is similar to many poems by Whitman without being clearly linked to any particular poem.
  - America! thee formulating, about 1881; loc.00621; xxx.00267; poetry 1 leaf 13 x 20.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder America! Thee formulating)
    A draft of a poem entitled America! thee formulating. The lines were incorporated as lines 90 and 91 in the poem Thy Mother with Thy Equal Brood, first published in 1881. On the verso are lines that appears to be trial titles: Voices at Early Candle-Light and Hurry-Notes.
  - [Sands Drifted], about 1879-1882; loc.04180; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands Drifted and Sands Drifted on the Shores of Sixty Years.
  - [Resumés], about 1879-1882; loc.04181; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands & Drift at Sixty-Three.
  - [? Songs], about 1879-1882; loc.04182; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands at Sixty-Three and Sands & Spray at 61.
  - [Names], about 1879-1882; loc.04184; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Noon & Sundown Songs and Sands on the Shores of 60 & after.
  - [Sands on the Shores of my 64th year], about 1883; loc.04185; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands on the Shores of my 64th year.
  - [Sands & Drift], about 1879-1883; loc.04224; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Shore Drift Sands at Sixty-One and Sands at 64.
  - [Shore Drift Sands at Sixty-One], about 1880; loc.04225; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Shore Drift Sands at Sixty-One and Drifted Sands at Sixty-One.
  - [Sands & Drift], about 1879-1882; loc.04227; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands & Drift from a life's melange.
  - [Wing-and-Wing], about 1881-1883; loc.04228; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands at 64.
  - [Sands on the Shores of my 60th year], about 1879; loc.04229; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands on the Shores of my 60th year.
  - [Sands at 61], about 1879-1882; loc.04230; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands at 61 and Sands Drifted on the Shores of Sixty Years.
  - [Drift Sands], about 1879-1882; loc.04231; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Drift Sands on the Shores of Sixty Years.
  - [Sands Drifted on the Shores], about 1879-1882; loc.04232; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands Drifted on the Shores of a Life in the 19th Century in the New World.
  - [Sands], about 1879-1882; loc.04237; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial titles and notes, including Sands on the Shores of 64 & '5.
  - [As half caught echoes], 1884; loc.04238; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial lines and notes for an unpublished poem. The first line begins, "As half caught echoes." The relationship of this manuscript to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [Drift Sands], about 1879-1882; loc.04239; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf 6 x 14 to 20.5 x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Drift Sands)
    Trial lines and notes for an unpublished poem entitled Drift Sands. The first line begins, "As we float idly."
  - Drift Sands., about 1888; loc.04183; xxx.00410; prose poetry correspondence 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder "Drift Sands")
    Draft lines and phrases under the title Drift Sands. Whitman never published a poem with this title, though this and several other closely related manuscripts seem to constitute working drafts for the couplet "As idly drifting down the ebb, / Such ripples, half-caught voices, echo from the shore," which appears before the final paragraph of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ). Most of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads was drawn from three previously published pieces (A Backward Glance on My Own Road [ 1884 ], How I Made a Book [ 1886 ], and My Book and I [ 1887 ]). The couplet, however, was not part of any of those earlier essays. On the reverse side of the manuscript is a letter to Whitman dated June 8, 1885.
  - Drift Sands, about 1888; loc.05999; xxx.00410; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder "Drift Sands")
    Two draft lines, with the title Drift Sands. Whitman never published a poem with this title, though this and several other closely related manuscripts seem to constitute working drafts for the couplet "As idly drifting down the ebb, / Such ripples, half-caught voices, echo from the shore," which appears before the final paragraph of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ). Most of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads was drawn from three previously published pieces (A Backward Glance on My Own Road [ 1884 ], How I Made a Book [ 1886 ], and My Book and I [ 1887 ]). The couplet, however, was not part of any of those earlier essays.
  - Notes and Flanges.—No. 1., about 1888; loc.04235; xxx.00410; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder "Drift Sands")